Don Yoder Collection of Wire Recordings
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
Don Yoder Collection of Wire Recordings 1950-1960
AFC 1970/004
Yoder, Don
manuscripts: 2 folders + sound wire reel containers.
21 sound wire reels: analog; 3 in.
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center Library of Congress, Washington, D.C. http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.home
Collection of field recordings of hymns and spirituals of Pennsylvania Dutch Evangelical United Brethren, United Christian, and Mennonite singers; humorous songs, secular folk songs, jokes, religious beliefs, tales, and conversations in Pennsylvania German; hymns, ballads, folk songs, tales, and ghost stories in English. Several interviews are about holidays, camp meetings, and traditional healing, including Sophia Bailer's discussion of Pennsylvania Dutch blessings for healing -- "brauche" -- also known as powwowing. Musical accompaniment includes guitar and fiddle for some recordings. One wire spool includes a radio broadcast from station WEEU of a program on "Pennsylvania Dutch folklore" presented by John B. Brendel.
Administrative Information
Arrangement
Organized by format into the following series: I. Manuscripts; II. Sound Recordings.
Indexes
Recording logs are available in the Folklife Reading Room, Library of Congress.
Additional Formats
Preservation tape reels: Washington, D.C.: Library of Congress Recording Laboratory, circa 1970. 4 sound tape reels: analog, 7 1/2 ips, mono.; 10 in. The sound recordings have been digitized from the preservation masters. Researchers can listen to the digital recordings in the Folklife Reading Room.
Related Material
Don Yoder Collection of Tape Recordings (AFC 2003/051).
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Custodial History
Library of Congress duplication project, circa 1970. During duplication, some of the 32 wire reels originally acquired were found to be blank; the blank reels were deaccessioned. The remaining original wire recordings were retained by the American Folklife Center, Archive of Folk Culture.
Bibliography
Boyer, Walter E., Albert F. Buffington, and Don Yoder. Songs along the Mahantongo. Lancaster: Pennsylvania Dutch Folklore Center, 1951.
Yoder, Don. Pennsylvania Spirituals. Lancaster, Pennsylvania: Pennsylvania Folklife Society, 1961.
Biographical Notes
Born in 1921, in Altoona, Pennsylvania, Don Yoder grew up immersed in the traditions of Pennsylvania German culture. Educated at Franklin and Marshall College (A.B., 1942 and B.D., 1945), and at the University of Chicago (Ph.D., 1947). Yoder was chair of the Department of Folklore and Folklife at the University of Pennsylvania from 1966-1969, and retired from teaching after 40 years. He authored and co-authored hundreds of publications, traveled and lectured widely, and held varied posts, including director of the Pennsylvania Folklife Society (which he co-founded), editor of Pennsylvania Folklife, president of the American Folklore Society, and Professor Emeritus of Folklife Studies, University of Pennsylvania. He is a member of Phi Beta Kappa, and has been elected fellow to the American Antiquarian Society and the American Genealogical Society, among others. He introduced the European concept and practice of folklife studies in the United States.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Brendel, John B., 1911-1971, speaker.; Bailer, Sophia, performer, interviewee.; Yoder, Don, collector.
Organizations
Evangelical United Brethren Church.; Mennonite Brethren in Christ.; United Christian Church.; United Zion Church.; WEEU (Radio station: Reading, Pa.)
Subjects
Ballads, English--Pennsylvania.; Camp meetings--Pennsylvania.; Field recordings--Pennsylvania.; Folk songs, English--Pennsylvania.; Folk songs, Pennsylvania German--Pennsylvania.; Ghost stories--Pennsylvania.; Healing--Pennsylvania--Religious aspects.; Humorous songs--Pennsylvania.; Hymns, English--Pennsylvania.; Hymns, German--Pennsylvania.; Mennonites--Pennsylvania--Hymns.; Pennsylvania Dutch--Pennsylvania--Folklore.; Pennsylvania Dutch--Pennsylvania--Music.; Pennsylvania Dutch--Pennsylvania--Religion.; Pennsylvania Dutch--Pennsylvania--Social life and customs.; Powwows (healers).; Revival hymns--Pennsylvania.; Tales--Pennsylvania.
Form/Genre
Field recordings.; Interviews.; Jokes.; Prayers.; Radio programs.
Scope and Content
Collection of field recordings of hymns and spirituals of Pennsylvania Dutch Evangelical United Brethren, United Christian, and Mennonite singers; humorous songs, secular folk songs, jokes, religious beliefs, tales, and conversations in Pennsylvania German; hymns, ballads, folk songs, tales, and ghost stories in English. Several interviews are about holidays, camp meetings, and traditional healing, including Sophia Bailer's discussion of Pennsylvania Dutch blessings for healing -- "brauche" -- also known as powwowing. Musical accompaniment includes guitar and fiddle for some recordings. One wire spool includes a radio broadcast from station WEEU of a program on "Pennsylvania Dutch folklore" presented by John B. Brendel.
Recorded by Don Yoder and others at various locations in the Pennsylvania Dutch area of eastern Pennsylvania in 1950-1951, 1960, and possibly on other dates. Locations include Lancaster County, Lebanon County, Schuylkill County, Lehigh County, and Berks County, Pennsylvania.
Various performers and interviewees including Emma L. Yoder, Harry Lewis, Beulah Mae Lewis, Oliver Franklin Follweiler, Harvey Brunner Musselman, Miriam Hollenbach, Aggie Osman, Valeria Gable, Florence Gable, Florence Deibler, Martin Sweigert, Sophia Bailer, William (Willie) Brown, Christian R. Longenecker, Charles Fassnacht, Ella Fassnacht, Wesley Pfautz Martin, Mrs. Wesley P. Martin, and others.
http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655343
Container List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - Collection finding aid, 13 pages. (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Documentation for sound recordings (original), 17 items. (Box 1)
    Original containers for wire reels.
  - Documentation for sound recordings (photocopies), 23 pages. (Box-folder 1/2)
    Photocopies of wire reels and original containers that have handwritten notes.
- Series II: Sound Recordings
  - Wire reel, recorded ca.1951-1960, AFC 1970/004: SR11; afc1970004_sr11; 17 selections.; Duration: 00:30:44.
    Includes folk songs and spoken word segments in Pennsylvania German and in English. The songs are sometimes sung a cappela, and sometimes accompanied by instruments. Several of the songs were published in the book Songs Along The Mahantongo. Recorded at the Pennsylvania Dutch Folklore Center (later the Pennsylvania Folklife Society).
  - Wire reel, recorded July 13, 1960, AFC 1970/004: SR12; afc1970004_sr12; 16 selections.; Duration: 00:15:45.
    Includes spirituals in Pennsylvania German and in English. The songs are sung a cappela. Sporadic, brief talk can be heard between songs. Many of the songs are included with text and notation in Pennsylvania Spirituals.
  - Wire reel, recorded ca. 1951-1960, AFC 1970/004: SR13; afc1970004_sr13pt1; afc1970004_sr13pt2; 43 selections.; Duration: 00:17:11 (part 1), 00:13:47 (part 2).
    Includes hymns and songs in Pennsylvania German.
  - Wire reel, recorded ca. 1951-1960, AFC 1970/004: SR14; afc1970004_sr14; 36 selections.; Duration: 00:31:16.
    Includes songs in Pennsylvania German and in English. Nine hymns in Pennsylvania German are repeated from SR12.
  - Wire reel, recorded ca. 1951-1960, AFC 1970/004: SR15; afc1970004_sr15; 24 selections.; Duration: 00:19:55.
    Includes religious songs in Pennsylvania German, as well as spirituals in Pennsylvania German and in English. The first thirteen songs are repeated from SR14. The latter group of songs appear, with text and musical notation, in Pennsylvania Spirituals.
  - Wire reel, recorded July 13, 1960, AFC 1970/004: SR16; afc1970004_sr16; 28 selections.; Duration: 00:11:20.
    All selections are fragments of spirituals sung in English by the same unidentified male singer, with no instrumental accompaniment.
  - Wire reel, recorded July 13, 1960, AFC 1970/004: SR17; afc1970004_sr17; 29 selections.; Duration: 00:22:02.
    Includes spirituals in Pennsylvania German and in English. Only one selection is in English.
  - Wire reel, recorded July 13, 1960, AFC 1970/004: SR18; afc1970004_sr18; 28 selections.; Duration: 00:30:56.
    Includes folks songs, spirituals, a counting rhyme, and a lullabye in Pennsylvania German. A prayer, possibly in Pennsylvania German, is sung. Also included are songs and ballads in English, and Pennsylvania German stories told in English.
  - Wire reel, recorded July 13, 1960, AFC 1970/004: SR19; afc1970004_sr19; 11 selections.; Duration: 00:12:45.
    Includes folk songs and spoken word passages in English.
  - Wire reel, recorded July 13, 1960, AFC 1970/004: SR20; afc1970004_sr20; 12 selections.; Duration: 00:31:24.
    Includes ballads and songs in English, and spoken word passages with some Pennsylvania German dialect mixed in. Sophia Bailer talks about powwowing.
  - Wire reel, recorded July 13, 1960, AFC 1970/004: SR21; afc1970004_sr21; 23 selections.; Duration: 00:17:48.
    Includes spirituals in Pennsylvania German and a brief statement in English.
  - Wire reel, recorded January 20, 1951, AFC 1970/004: SR22; afc1970004_sr22; 20 selections.; Duration: 00:14:32.
    Includes spirituals in Pennsylvania German and in English.
  - Wire reel, recorded July 13, 1960, AFC 1970/004: SR23; afc1970004_sr23; 27 selections.; Duration: 00:15:59.
    Includes spirituals in Pennsylvania German.
  - Wire reel, recorded July 13, 1960, AFC 1970/004: SR24; afc1970004_sr24; 8 selections.; Duration: 00:14:57.
  - Wire reel, recorded July 13, 1960, AFC 1970/004: SR25; afc1970004_sr25; 61 selections.; Duration: 00:19:00.
    Includes folk songs in German and Pennsylvania German, songs in Pennsylvania German, a story in Pennsylvania German and English, songs in English, and jokes in Pennsylvania German (with some English).
  - Wire reel, recorded ca. 1950, AFC 1970/004: SR26; afc1970004_sr26; 37 selections.; Duration: 21:05.
  - Wire reel, recorded July 13, 1960, AFC 1970/004: SR27; afc1970004_sr27; 32 selections.; Duration: 00:26:13.
    Includes spirituals in Pennsylvania German and in English, and a Pennsylvania German-style German hymn.
  - Wire reel, recorded July 13, 1960, AFC 1970/004: SR28; afc1970004_sr28; 25 selections.; Duration: 00:15:14.
    Includes folk songs, a lullabye, a joke, and a parody of a spiritual in Pennsylvania German; a humorous Pennsylvania German song in English; and a humorous song, folk songs, and a local prison ballad in English.
  - Wire reel, recorded ca. 1951-1960, AFC 1970/004: SR29; afc1970004_sr29; 3 selections.; Duration: 00:04:09.
    Includes two Pennsylvania German folk songs, and a conversation in English and Pennsylvania German between a male interviewer and a young girl.
  - Wire reel, recorded ca. 1951-1960, AFC 1970/004: SR30; afc1970004_sr30; 28 selections.; Duration: 00:23:59.
    Includes stories and folk songs in Pennsylvania German and other spoke-word segments, also in Pennsylvania German; also stories and an evangelical song (with a bawdy parody of the same song), and spoken-word segments in English.
  - Wire reel, recorded ca. 1952, AFC 1970/004: SR32; afc1970004_sr32; 4 selections.; Duration: 00:14:45.
    Includes three recordings of radio broadcasts, and a spoken word segment, all in Pennsylvania German. John Brendel was the host for at least two of the broadcasts.